Alexander, Gabriel Additional Arbitration Files 5602
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Gabriel Alexander Additional Arbitration Files
1967-1976
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Alexander, Gabriel
5602
11 cubic feet
11 linear ft.
Blueprints (reprographic copies), case files, photographs.
Case files regarding Gabriel Alexander's arbitration work.
3833907
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, April 11, 2013
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 20, 2019
Biographical / Historical
IIndependent arbitrator, attorney and adjunct professor of labor arbitration.
Gabriel N. Alexander holds a JD from the University of Michigan (1933). He was a partner in the law firm of Alexander and Alexander (1933-1948) after which he served as hearing officer for the Automotive Section of the U.S. War Labor Board (1945-1946).
Alexander was impartial umpire for General Motors Corporation vs. the International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace and Agricultural Implement Workers of America (UAW) (1948-1954), Bower Roller Bearing Company vs. UAW (1956- 1959), and Chrysler Corporation vs. UAW; impartial chairman for Jones & Laughlin Steel Company vs. United Steelworkers of America (USWA) (1960-1961), Major League Baseball Clubs vs. Players Association (1972-1974), Clark Equipment Company vs. UAW (1966-1971), and Armco Incorporated vs. USWA; arbitrator for Bethlehem Steel Company vs. USWA (1954-1955); permanent arbitrator for International Harvester vs. UAW (1964-1976), and John Deere Horicon Works vs. UAW (1968-1971). Additionally, Alexander served as a member on arbitration panels for General Motors Corporation vs. United Rubber, Cork, Linoleum and Plastic Workers of America, Greyhound Bus Lines vs. Amalgamated Transit Union, American Airlines Corporation vs. Airline Stewards and Stewardesses Association, and U.S. Steel Corporation vs. Salaried Employees Association.
Scope and Contents
Case files for the International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers (IUE) include IUE vs. Vickers Incorporated (1954-1964) on issues of holiday, reclassification, seniority, work assignment, layoff and contracting out; IUE vs. Automatic Music Incorporated (1960-1961) on the issue of job evaluation; IUE vs. Wayne Pump Company on issues of recall, seniority, and back pay; IUE vs. Allen Bradley Company (1966-1967) on issues of position classification and wage rate; IUE vs. Ironrite Incorporated (1955-1959) on issues of layoff, work assignment, wages, position classification, reporting pay and arbitrability; IUE vs. Square D. Company (1954) on the issue of dismissal; and IUE vs. General Motors Corporation (1947-1949, 1956) on issues of dismissal, overtime, discipline, wage rate, layoff, shift preference, reporting pay, and seniority.
The arbitration case files of Gabriel Alexander include opinions and awards, statements of fact of cases, correspondence (carbons and originals) of Alexander with companies and unions involved in arbitration, transcripts of arbitration proceedings, transcripts of witness testimony, exhibits (company and union), including photographs and blueprints, Alexander's manuscript notes on individual cases, agreements (between company and union), company and union briefs, and financial materials (bills, receipts, letters) regarding services of Alexander as arbitrator.
Major cases that Alexander arbitrated include the United Steelworkers of America (USWA) vs. Jones & Laughlin Steel Company (1960-1961) on issues of seniority, discipline, suspension, scheduling, work assignment, wages, dismissal, supervisor performing bargaining unit work, working conditions, and other individual issues; USWA vs. Bethlehem Steel Corporation (1955) on issues of seniority, contracting out, wage incentive, position classification, and work assignment; USWA vs. White Pine Copper Company (1963-1970) on issues of seniority, work assignment, wages, discipline, promotion, and overtime; USWA vs. McLouth Steel Company (1956-1968) on the issue of wages; USWA vs. Crucible Steel Company of America (1929); USWA vs. Allegheny Ludlum Steel Corporation on issues of seniority, incentives, holiday pay, discipline, and overtime; and USWA vs. Evans Products Company (1955-1962) on issues of transfer, position classification, work assignments, work rules, and recall.
Other case files involving USWA include USWA vs. Pittsburgh Steel Company (1960, 1963) on the issue of seniority; USWA vs. Inland Steel Company (1957-1967) on issues of discipline, wages, and overtime; USWA vs. Palmer-Bee Company (1957-1959) on issues of dismissal, wages, vacation pay, and performance appraisal; USWA vs. Hanna Mining Company (1957-1970) on issues of arbitrability, seniority, working conditions, wages, scheduling, contracting out, and pension dispute; and additional cases (1955-1972) involving the USWA and a number of smaller companies.
Case files for the International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America (UAW) include UAW vs. International Harvester (1964-1976) on issues of discipline, seniority, work assignment, wages, and dismissal; UAW vs. Bower Roller Bearing Company, Division of Federal Mogul Bower Bearings Incorporated (1955-1966) on issues of dismissal, probationary period, discipline, and seniority; UAW vs. Clark Equipment Company (1966-1970) on issues of seniority, overtime, work assignment, supervisors performing bargaining unit work, discipline, and dismissal; UAW vs. John Deere Horicon Works/Deere & Company (1968-1970) on issues of discipline, wages, overtime, contracting out, seniority, classification, and recall; UAW vs. Standard Cotton Products (1956-1965) on issues of layoff, dismissal, seniority, representation, and discipline; and UAW vs. General Motors Corporation (1958-1969) on issues of work assignment, layoff, vacation, dismissal, promotion, time claim, improper assignment, cost-of-living adjustment, and wage classification; additional cases involving the UAW.
Case files for the United Mine Workers of America (UMWA) include UMWA vs. Pennsalt Chemical Corporation (1957-1962) on issues of discipline, layoff, classification, and grievance procedure; UMWA vs. Pennsylvania Salt Manufacturing Company (1954-1959) on issues of promotion, wages, discipline, overtime, and work load; UMWA vs. Celanese Chemical Company (1958-1967) on issues of meal period and others; additional cases involving the UMWA.
Case files for the International Association of Machinists (IAM) include IAM vs. Whirlpool Corporation (1957-1958) on issues of position classification, discipline, job location, dismissal, wage incentive, job evaluation, vacation schedule, layoff, and suspension; IAM vs. John Deere Horicon Works/Deere & Company (1960-1961) on issues of wages and job evaluation; IAM vs. United Air Lines (1960-1967) on issues of holiday pay, suspension, layoff, seniority, working conditions, and furlough; and IAM vs. Paramount Die Casting Company (1955-1962) on issues of seniority, transfer, discipline, dismissal, wages, and work assignment outside position classification.
Case files for the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers (IBEW) include IBEW vs. Indiana and Michigan Electric Company (1965-1971) on issues of discipline and promotion, and additional cases (1974-1975) involving the IBEW and various small companies.
Case files for the International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers (IUE) include IUE vs. Vickers Incorporated (1954-1964) on issues of holiday, reclassification, seniority, work assignment, layoff and contracting out; IUE vs. Automatic Music Incorporated (1960-1961) on the issue of job evaluation; IUE vs. Wayne Pump Company on issues of recall, seniority, and back pay; IUE vs. Allen Bradley Company (1966- 1967) on issues of position classification and wage rate; IUE vs. Ironrite Incorporated (1955-1959) on issues of layoff, work assignment, wages, position classification, reporting pay and arbitrability; IUE vs. Square D. Company (1954) on the issue of dismissal; and IUE vs. General Motors Corporation (1947-1949, 1956) on issues of dismissal, overtime, discipline, wage rate, layoff, shift preference, reporting pay, and seniority.
Other cases include Swift and Company vs. the Amalgamated Meat Cutters and Butcher Workmen of North America, United Packinghouse, Food and Allied Workers, and the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America (IBT) (1955-1971) on issues of discipline, demotions, guaranteed wage, compensation, dismissal, voluntary-quit, accident benefits and sickness benefits, holiday pay, wages, vacation pay, seniority, reinstatement, layoff, overtime, and classification.
Additional case files include the IBT vs. Eastern Michigan Company on the issue of wages: IBT vs. American Bakery Company on issues of overtime, and wage rates; and IBT vs. L.C. Clark Hauling Company Incorporated on the issue of dismissal (1955-1958); United Rubber, Cork, Linoleum and Plastic Workers (URW) vs. General Motors Corporation on issues of discipline, seniority, reduction in force, and equalization of time; URW vs. Industrial Rubber Goods Company on issues of job evaluation and wage incentive; URW vs. Dayton Rubber Company (1956-1963); United Papermakers and Paperworkers (UPP) vs. Allied Paper Company and Sutherland Paper Company on issues of reduction of force and increased work load; UPP vs. S.D. Warren Company on issues of dismissal and layoff; and UPPA vs. Owens-Illinois Glass Company, Forest Products Division on issues of wages and incentives (1957-1964).
Other case files include Oil, Chemical and Atomic Workers International Union of America (OCAW) vs. U.S. Industrial Chemical Company on issues of overtime and reporting pay; OCAW vs. International Salt Company on issues of position classification, wage rates, and work assignment; OCAW vs. Monsanto Chemical Company on issues of dismissal, and overtime; OCAW vs. Wyandotte Chemical Corporation on the issue of discipline; and OCAW vs. Phillips Petroleum Company on issues of downgrading, layoff, and bumping (1956-1962).
Additionally, there are case files for individual cases with United Dairy and Bakery Workers (1956-1961), Pattern Makers League of North America (1958-1972), Salaried Employees Association (1968-1973), Major League Baseball Players Association (1972, 1974), and other miscellaneous unions.
Also, rules of procedure, award summaries, opinions and awards of the arbitrators, company and union briefs, exhibits, transcripts, and general correspondence for cases of 245 Communications Workers of America members striking Southern Bell Telephone and Telegraph Company and dismissed for misconduct and property destruction (1955). The arbitrators hearing the cases were Whitley P. McCoy (former director, Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service), Carl R. Schedley (former associate director, Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service), Gabriel N. Alexander, and Dudley E. Whiting. The arbitrators were given full power to sustain, set back or modify the dismissal penalty.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5120: Southern Bell Telephone and Telegraph Company and the Communications Workers of America Arbitration Files 5133: Gabriel Alexander Arbitration Files 5678: Gabriel Alexander Additional Arbitration Files 5789: Gabriel Alexander Additional Arbitration Files
Arbitration, Industrial. Agricultural machine industry. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Aircraft industry. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Airlines. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Automobile industry. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Cement Industries. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Chemical industry. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Container industry. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Cotton manufacture. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Electric industries. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Machine industry. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Rubber industry. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Salt industry. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Shipbuilding industry. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Steel industry. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. United States. Cases.; Contracting out. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Employee fringe benefits. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Employees, Dismissal of. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Employees, Transfer of. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Grievance procedures. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Hours of labor. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Labor discipline. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Layoffs. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Paid nonwork time. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Performance appraisal. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Position classification. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Promotions. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Retirement. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Seniority, Employee. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Trade-union representatives. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Wages. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Work assignments. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Work rules. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Working conditions. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Alexander, Gabriel; McCoy, Whitley P.; Schedley, Carl R.; Whiting, Dudley E.; Allegheny Ludlum Steel Corporation.; Amalgamated Meat Cutters and Butcher Workmen of North America; Bethlehem Steel Corporation.; Bower Roller Bearing Company.; Celanese Chemical Company.; Clark Equipment Company.; Communications Workers of America; Crucible Steel Company of America.; Deere & Company.; Deere & Company. Horicon Works.; Evans Products Company.; General Motors Corporation.; Hanna Mining Company.; Indiana and Michigan Electric Company; Indiana Steel Company.; Inland Steel Company.; International Association of Machinists.; International Association of Machinists. Republic Lodge.; International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers.; International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America.; International Harvester Company.; International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers.; International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America.; Ironrite, Inc.; Jones & Laughlin Steel Company.; L.C. Clark Hauling Company, Inc.; Major League Baseball Players Association.; McLouth Steel Company.; Oil, Chemical, and Atomic Workers International Union; Owens-Illinois Glass Company. Forest Products Division.; Paramount Die Casting Company.; Pattern Makers League of North America.; Pennsalt Chemical Corporation.; Pennsylvania Salt Manufacturing Company.; Phillips Petroleum Company.; Pittsburgh Steel Company.; Salaried Employees Association.; Southern Bell Telephone and Telegraph Company.; Standard Cotton Products.; Swift and Company.; United Air Lines, Inc.; United Dairy and Bakery Workers.; United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America.; United Mine Workers of America.; United Packinghouse Workers of America.; United Packinghouse, Food and Allied Workers.; United Papermakers and Paperworkers.; United Rubber, Cork, Linoleum, and Plastic Workers.; United Steelworkers of America; Vickers Incorporated.; Whirlpool Corporation.; White Pine Copper Company.
3833907
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 441, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 440, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 442, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 443, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 444, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 445, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 446, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 447, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 448, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 449, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 450, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 451, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 452, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 453, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 454, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 455, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 456, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 457, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 458, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 459, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 460, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 461, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 462, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 463, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 464, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 465, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 466, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 467, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 468, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 469, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 470, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 471, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 396, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 397, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 398, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 399, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 400, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 401, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 402, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 403, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 404, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 405, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 406, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 407, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 408, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 409, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 410, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 411, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 412, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 413, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 414, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 415, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 416, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 417, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 418, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 419, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 420 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 421, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 422, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 423, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 424, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 425, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 426, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 427, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 428, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 429, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 430, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 431, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 432, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 433, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 434, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 435, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 436, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 437, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 438, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Case No. 439, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- International Harvester Company and UAW, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Sub 2, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Local - Joint Pension Board, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Scope and Contents
  November 4, 1969
- International Harvester Company Expedited Arbitration Cases Settled Prior to Trial (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Expedited Decisions (Box 3, Folder 14)
- International Harvester Company - Expedited Arbitration Information (Box 3, Folder 15)
- International Harvester (Expedited Case Information) (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Expedited Work Sheets (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Brief on Case #334 Local #226 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Local 226 Case No. 334 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Local 226 Case No. 333, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Local 1336 Case No. 336, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Local 1301 Case No. 337, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Local 6 Case 338, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Local 1309 Case No. 339, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Local 1301, Tractor Works Case No. 340, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Local 1301, Tractor Works Case No.341, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Local 817, Louisville Works Case No. 342, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Local Case No. 342, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Local 187, E-47602, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Local Case No. 344, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Local Case No. 345, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- International Harvester Company and UAW Local 658, Case No. 346, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- International Harvester Company and UAW, Springfield Works Case No. 347, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 10)